GPS on smartphones is really convenient, isn't it?
스마트폰 GPS 정말 편리하죠?
I'm embarrassed to admit I have a terrible sense of direction
부끄럽지만 저는 길치라서
Without GPS and smartphone map apps I can barely get to my destination
GPS와 스마트폰 지도 앱이 없으면 목적지까지 제대로 가지도 못해요
But GPS relies on signals from space
하지만 GPS는 원래 우주에서 오는 전파에 의존하기 때문에
It doesn't work when you're in a tunnel or on a ferry out at sea
터널 안에 있을 때나 페리를 타고 바다 위에 있을 때는 사용할 수 없고
And it can be disabled by malicious jamming signals
악의적인 방해 전파로도 무력화될 수 있어요
But is there a way to measure position with high precision without GPS?
그런데 GPS 없이 초고정밀로 위치를 측정하는 방법이 있을까요?
Actually, a technology called quantum navigation using ultra-cold atoms is rapidly developing
사실 지금 극저온 원자를 사용한 양자 항법이라는 기술이 급속히 발전하고 있습니다
In 2025, there was news that Boeing and the British Navy succeeded in demonstration tests
2025년에는 보잉과 영국 해군이 실증 실험에 성공했다는 뉴스도 있었어요
Today, I'll explain why cooling atoms allows us to determine position
오늘은 왜 원자를 냉각하면 위치를 알 수 있는지
Let's look at how it works
그 원리를 설명해 드리겠습니다
First, let's talk about the most classical method of knowing your position without GPS
먼저 GPS를 사용하지 않고 자신의 위치를 아는 가장 고전적인 방법부터 이야기해 볼까요
Have you ever heard of the speed unit called "knots"?
여러분 노트(knot)라는 속도 단위 들어보신 적 있나요?
It's used for ship speeds, right?
배의 속도 같은 데 사용하죠
This unit actually comes from a measurement method invented by ancient sailors
이 단위는 사실 옛날 뱃사람들이 생각해낸 측정법에서 유래했어요
They tied knots at regular intervals on a rope
로프에 일정 간격으로 매듭을 묶고
And threw it into the sea
그것을 바다에 던집니다
They counted how many knots passed while the sand in an hourglass fell
모래시계의 모래가 떨어지는 동안 몇 개의 매듭이 지나갔는지 세면
This told them their speed
속도를 알 수 있어요
It's a really clever method, isn't it?
정말 똑똑한 방법이죠?
Distance traveled can be calculated by multiplying speed and time
이동 거리는 속도와 시간을 곱하면 계산할 수 있어요
It's a formula you learn in middle school but this is the basis of inertial navigation
중학교에서 배운 공식이지만 이것이 관성 항법의 기본이에요
But in real movement, speed changes, right?
하지만 실제 이동에서는 속도가 변하죠?
Accelerating and decelerating
가속하거나 감속하거나
In that case, you can plot speed versus time on a graph and find the distance traveled from the area under the curve
그런 경우에는 속도와 시간의 그래프를 그려서 그 면적을 구하면 이동 거리를 알 수 있어요
This is what we call integration in mathematics
이것이 수학에서 말하는 적분이에요
But modern aircraft and ships commonly measure acceleration rather than velocity to determine position
하지만 현대의 비행기나 배에서는 속도가 아닌 가속도를 측정해서 위치를 구하는 것이 일반적이에요
Why measure acceleration instead of velocity?
왜 속도가 아니라 가속도를 측정할까요?
When you're on an airplane you feel takeoff and landing with your body, right?
비행기를 탔을 때 이륙이나 착륙 순간은 몸으로 느껴지죠?
But during stable flight, you can't even tell if you're moving without looking out the window
하지만 안정 비행 중에는 창밖을 보지 않으면 자신이 움직이고 있는지조차 모릅니다
In other words, it's difficult to directly measure velocity inside a vehicle moving at constant speed
즉, 등속 운동하는 탈것 안에서 직접 속도를 측정하기는 어려워요
Measuring velocity requires an external reference
속도를 측정하려면 외부 기준이 필요합니다
But acceleration can be measured without an external reference
하지만 가속도는 외부 기준 없이도 측정할 수 있어요
That's why inertial navigation measures acceleration and integrates it twice to find position
그래서 관성 항법은 가속도를 측정해서 두 번 적분하여 위치를 구합니다
It's a self-contained system that can work on its own without external information
외부 정보 없이 자기 자신만으로 완결되는 자립형 시스템이에요
But there's a big problem here
하지만 여기에 큰 문제가 있습니다
If there's a slight error in the accelerometer that error accumulates with each integration
가속도계에 약간의 오차가 있으면 적분할 때마다 그 오차가 누적됩니다
Moreover, since distance is calculated by integrating acceleration twice, the error grows proportionally to the square of time
게다가 이동 거리는 가속도를 두 번 적분해서 계산하므로 오차는 시간의 제곱에 비례해서 커져요
Even with today's high-precision aircraft accelerometers the error reaches about 6.5 km after 10 hours
현재 항공기용 고정밀 가속도계로도 10시간이면 약 6.5km나 어긋납니다
This makes it unusable for long-distance navigation
이래서는 장거리 항행에 사용할 수 없어요
That's why we currently use GPS corrections periodically to reset the error
그래서 현재는 GPS로 정기적으로 보정해서 오차를 리셋하고 있습니다
Aircraft, ships, smartphones - they all use this method
비행기도 배도 스마트폰도 다 이 방식이에요
So current positioning technology requires external information like GPS
그래서 현재의 위치 측정 기술에서는 GPS 같은 외부 정보가 필수적이에요
But GPS has weaknesses too
하지만 GPS에도 약점이 있습니다
Since it uses radio waves from satellites naturally it can't work where signals can't reach
인공위성의 전파를 사용하므로 당연히 전파가 닿지 않는 곳에서는 사용할 수 없어요
For example, underwater
예를 들어 수중
GPS cannot measure the position of submarines or underwater drones
잠수함이나 수중 드론의 위치는 GPS로 측정할 수 없습니다
It also doesn't work in tunnels, underground spaces, or urban canyons
터널이나 지하 공간, 빌딩 숲 사이에서도 사용할 수 없어요
What's even scarier is malicious attacks
더 무서운 것은 악의적인 공격입니다
Spoofing sends fake GPS signals to cause position errors and jamming disables GPS with interference signals
가짜 GPS 신호를 보내 위치를 오인하게 하는 스푸핑이나 방해 전파로 GPS를 무력화하는 재밍
These are real threats in conflict zones and near borders
분쟁 지역이나 그 국경 부근에서는 현실적인 위협이 되고 있어요
This is where quantum mechanics comes in
여기서부터 양자역학의 출번입니다
In 1924, a physicist named Louis de Broglie proposed a remarkable theory
1924년, 루이 드 브로이라는 물리학자가 놀라운 이론을 제창했습니다
"All matter has wave-like properties" This is called matter waves
"모든 물질은 파동으로서의 성질을 가진다" 이것을 물질파라고 합니다
The wavelength λ can be expressed by this formula
그 파장 λ는 이런 식으로 나타낼 수 있어요
h is Planck's constant, m is mass, v is velocity In other words, slower-moving objects have longer wavelengths
h는 플랑크 상수, m은 질량, v는 속도 즉 느리게 움직이는 것일수록 파장이 길어집니다
Just as light, which was thought to be a wave also has particle-like properties
파동이라고 여겨졌던 빛이 입자로서의 성질도 함께 가지듯이
Atoms, which were thought to be particles also have wave-like properties at the same time
입자라고 여겨졌던 원자도 파동으로서의 성질을 동시에 가지고 있어요
Have you ever seen light interference patterns?
빛의 간섭무늬 보신 적 있나요?
When light waves with matching wavelengths collide they create bright and dark stripe patterns
파장이 같은 빛끼리 부딪히면 밝고 어두운 줄무늬가 생기는 현상이에요
Since atoms also have wave properties, they can do the same thing but there's a problem as they are
원자도 파동의 성질을 가지므로 같은 것을 할 수 있지만 그대로는 문제가 있어요
Hot atoms move at random velocities
뜨거운 원자는 제각각의 속도로 움직입니다
Random velocities mean random wavelengths
속도가 제각각이면 파장도 제각각
This causes the interference pattern to blur
이러면 간섭무늬가 흐려져 버려요
That's why we cool the atoms
그래서 원자를 냉각합니다
Cooling slows them down and narrows the velocity distribution
냉각하면 움직임이 느려지고 속도 분포가 좁아집니다
The wavelengths align
파장이 일치해요
Only then can we create clean interference
이래야 비로소 깨끗한 간섭을 일으킬 수 있습니다
But how do you cool atoms?
그런데 원자를 냉각한다는 건 어떻게 하는 걸까요?
Do you put them in a freezer?
냉동고에 넣어서 냉각할까요?
Actually, we use a literally cooler method
사실 더 말 그대로 '쿨'한 방법을 사용합니다
We cool them using lasers
바로 레이저로 냉각하는 거예요
When an atom absorbs a photon, it receives the photon's momentum and gets pushed
원자가 광자를 흡수하면 광자의 운동량을 받아 밀려납니다
If we shine a laser opposite to the atom's direction of travel, the atom slows down
원자의 진행 방향과 반대로 레이저를 쏘면 원자가 감속해요
We can also selectively slow only fast atoms using the Doppler effect
게다가 도플러 효과를 이용해서 빠른 원자만 선택적으로 감속시킬 수 있어요
Approaching atoms see a higher frequency and resonate
다가오는 원자는 주파수가 높게 보이므로 공명합니다
Receding atoms see a lower frequency and don't resonate
멀어지는 원자는 주파수가 낮게 보이므로 공명하지 않아요
With laser cooling, we can reach temperatures very close to absolute zero -273.15 degrees Celsius
레이저 냉각을 사용하면 거의 절대영도 -273.15도 바로 근처까지 냉각할 수 있어요
We can make it colder than outer space
무려 우주 공간보다 차갑게 만들 수 있습니다
So what do we do with these cooled atoms?
그럼 냉각한 원자로 무엇을 할까요?
Now we move from cooling to a different laser operation
여기서부터는 냉각과는 다른 레이저 조작 이야기입니다
We make the cooled atoms interfere to measure acceleration
냉각한 원자에 간섭을 일으켜서 가속도를 측정합니다
There's a light-based interferometer called the Mach-Zehnder interferometer
빛을 사용한 간섭계 마흐-젠더 간섭계라는 것이 있습니다
Light is split into two paths by a half-mirror
빛을 반투명 거울로 두 경로로 나누고
The light from each path is then recombined
각 경로를 지난 빛을 다시 합류시킵니다
When there's a path difference, interference patterns form
이때 경로차가 있으면 간섭무늬가 생겨요
Atom interferometers work on the same principle
원자 간섭계도 기본은 같습니다
The key point is that laser pulses can manipulate atomic paths
포인트는 레이저 펄스로 원자의 경로를 조작할 수 있다는 것
Applying laser pulses corresponds to splitting light at a half-mirror or reflecting off a mirror
레이저를 쏘는 조작이 반투명 거울의 빛 분리나 거울 반사에 대응할 수 있어요
When two lasers with slightly different frequencies hit an atom the atom's internal state and momentum change simultaneously
원자에 주파수가 약간 다른 두 개의 레이저를 쏘면 원자의 내부 상태와 운동량이 동시에 변합니다
This is called Raman transition
이것을 라만 전이라고 합니다
By controlling the atomic path with lasers
레이저로 원자가 나아가는 경로를 제어함으로써
We can create interference due to path differences
경로차에 의한 간섭을 일으킬 수 있어요
Atom interferometers use three laser pulses
원자 간섭계에서는 세 번의 레이저 펄스를 사용합니다
The first laser pulse splits the atom creating a superposition of ground state |g⟩ and excited state |e⟩
첫 번째 레이저 펄스는 원자를 분할하여 바닥 상태 |g⟩와 들뜬 상태 |e⟩의 중첩 상태를 만듭니다
It serves the same role as a half-mirror in optical systems
광학계에서의 반투명 거울과 같은 역할을 합니다
The second laser pulse reverses the paths
두 번째 레이저 펄스는 경로를 반전시킵니다
It swaps the ground state |g⟩ and excited state |e⟩
바닥 상태 |g⟩와 들뜬 상태 |e⟩를 교환합니다
This corresponds to mirror reflection in optical systems
광학계에서의 거울 반사에 대응해요
The final laser pulse superimposes the two paths to create interference
마지막 레이저 펄스는 두 경로를 중첩시켜 간섭을 일으킵니다
It serves as a half-mirror, just like the first pulse
처음과 마찬가지로 반투명 거울 역할이에요
In this way, three laser pulses can realize a Mach-Zehnder interferometer with atoms
이렇게 세 번의 레이저 펄스로 마흐-젠더 간섭계를 원자로도 실현할 수 있습니다
If there's acceleration the two paths experience different force histories
만약 가속도가 있으면 두 경로를 지난 원자가 받는 힘의 이력이 달라집니다
This difference appears as a phase shift
그 차이가 위상차로 나타납니다
The phase difference Δφ can be written as this formula
위상차 Δφ는 이런 식으로 쓸 수 있어요
This phase difference can ultimately be observed as the probability of being in ground state |g⟩
이 위상차는 최종적으로 바닥 상태 |g⟩에 있을 확률로 관측할 수 있습니다
By using many atoms and measuring statistically we can determine the acceleration
많은 원자를 사용해서 통계적으로 측정하면 가속도를 알 수 있어요
Comparing with conventional MEMS accelerometers shows that atom interferometers have extremely high precision
기존의 MEMS 가속도계와 비교해 보면 원자 간섭계의 정밀도가 극히 높다는 것을 알 수 있습니다
The precision of atom interferometers is around 10⁻⁹ to 10⁻¹² m/s²
원자 간섭계의 정밀도는 10⁻⁹~10⁻¹² m/s² 정도
This means an error of only about 65 cm for a 10-hour flight
이러면 10시간 비행에도 오차가 약 65cm 정도
Long-duration high-precision positioning is possible without GPS
GPS 없이도 장시간 고정밀 위치 측정이 가능합니다
Atom interferometers are based on atomic transition frequencies which are fundamental constants of nature
원자 간섭계는 원자의 전이 주파수라는 자연의 기본 상수를 기준으로 합니다
Planck's constant and the speed of light are the same everywhere in the universe, at all times
플랑크 상수나 광속은 우주 어디서든 언제든 같습니다
That's why such precise measurements are possible
그래서 고정밀 측정이 가능한 거예요
You might be thinking "It might work in theory but can it really be put into practical use?"
"이론적으로는 될지 몰라도 정말 실용화할 수 있을까?" 라고 생각한 분도 계실 겁니다
Actually, demonstration tests have already succeeded
사실 이미 실증 실험이 성공했습니다
Boeing, the famous aircraft manufacturer achieved a 4-hour GPS-free flight in 2025
유명한 비행기 제조사인 보잉은 2025년에 4시간 GPS 없이 비행에 성공했습니다
Q-CTRL, an Australian startup company achieved 22m precision with a Cessna aircraft
Q-CTRL이라는 호주 스타트업 기업은 세스나기로 22m 정밀도를 달성하고
They won Time magazine's 2025 Best Inventions award
타임지의 2025년 최고의 발명상을 수상했습니다
The British Navy has also succeeded in submarine tests
영국 해군도 잠수함에서의 시험에 성공했습니다
While still in the research stage it's attracting worldwide attention as next-generation positioning technology
아직 연구 단계이지만 차세대 위치 측정 기술로 전 세계에서 주목받고 있습니다
There are still many challenges like device miniaturization and cost reduction
아직 장치의 소형화나 비용 절감 등 과제도 많습니다
But advances in semiconductor lasers and atom chip technology used in quantum computers are bringing it closer to practical use each year
하지만 반도체 레이저의 발전이나 양자 컴퓨터에도 응용되는 아톰칩 기술의 발전으로 해마다 실용화에 가까워지고 있어요
Quantum mechanics might seem like a mysterious and strange world
양자역학이라고 하면 신비로운 세계라는 이미지가 있을지도 모릅니다
But like quantum navigation it's working as the foundation for technologies that benefit our daily lives
하지만 양자 항법처럼 우리 생활에 도움이 되는 기술의 기초로 활약하고 있어요
Just as smartphone GPS became commonplace
스마트폰의 GPS가 당연해진 것처럼
Quantum navigation might become commonplace someday too
언젠가 양자 항법이 당연해지는 날이 올지도 모르겠네요
Until next time, take care!
그럼 다음 영상에서 만나요, 안녕히 계세요!